Guide to the George H. Love Interviews, September-October 1988 AIS.1991.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
George H. Love Interviews
September-October 1988
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Love, George H.
Amatucci, Frances M.
University of Pittsburgh. Press
AIS.1991.05
0.31 Linear Feet (plus 12 audio cassettes)
Mr. George H. Love was interviewed eleven times between September 19 and October 24, 1988 at the request of Wesley W. Posvar, Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, in recognition of Love's contribution to American business. The collection contains a complete transcript of the interviews and 12 cassette tapes (19 hrs 46 mins). A digital reproduction of the transcript is available online.
Scope and Content Notes
Eleven interviews were conducted in George Love's home in Pittsburgh between September 19 and October 24, 1988, by Frances M. Amatucci at the request of Wesley W. Posvar, Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, in recognition of Love's contribution to American business. At the time, Ms. Amatucci was a doctoral candidate in strategic planning and policy at the Joseph M. Katz Graduate School of Business at the University of Pittsburgh. The 12 cassette tapes (19 hrs 46 mins) were transcribed by Christine Boyer (University of Pittsburgh Press staff) and edited by Catherine Marshall (University of Pittsburgh Press managing editor). Mr. Love, Mrs. Lois O-Connor (secretary to Mr. Love), and Ms. Amatucci reviewed and corrected the transcripts. Frederick A. Hetzel, Director of the University of Pittsburgh Press at the time, supervised the project.
The interviews are bound in a book-like binding that comprises 386 pages. It also contains an Index of Names which is meant to be a rough guide to the places in the interviews where Love mentions certain figures well known in the corporate world. The page number is generally the beginning of a passage where that person is discussed.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Biography
George Hutchinson Love was born on September 4, 1900 in Johnstown, Pa., where he spent his boyhood years. After graduation from Phillips Exeter Academy in New Hampshire (1918), Princeton University (1922) and Harvard Business School (1924), he worked for Lee-Higginson Company, an investment banking concern, as a salesman in Chicago. He went on to manage the office in St. Louis. He moved to Pittsburgh in 1926 when he entered his uncle's coal business, Union Collieries Company, as assistant to the president. He shortly became president in 1933, serving until 1943.
For some fifty years, Love was deeply involved in the coal industry. He became executive vice president and chairman of the executive committee of Consolidation Coal Company in New York in 1943. A year later, Consolidation took over Union Collieries' properties, and in 1945, it merged with Pittsburgh Coal Company to become Pittsburgh Consolidation Coal Company with Love as president. When the name was later changed to Consolidation Coal Company, Love became chairman serving in this capacity until 1972. He was the coal industry's chief negotiator with John L. Lewis and his United Mine Workers union in the 1940s and 1950s. Together they formed the National Coal Policy Conference to deal with the federal government on matters relating to the industry.
Love served as vice chairman of National Steel Corporation (1959-1961) and chairman of M.A. Hanna Company of Cleveland (1956-1961). He also served on the boards of Mellon Bank, General Electric, Union Carbide, and Chrysler. When Chrysler encountered a management crisis in the 1960s, Love was elected chairman on the board (1961-1966). He was responsible for the financial turnaround of the company and placed it once again in the black. Love died at age 90 in Pittsburgh on July 25, 1991 from complications from emphysema.
Acquisition Information
Gift executed by agreement dated December 6, 1989 and signed by Mrs. Lois O'Connor (Mr. Love's secretary) with power of attorney. Received by the Archives Service Center in 1991 from the University of Pittsburgh Press.
Previous Citation
George H. Love Interviews, September-October 1988, AIS.1991.05, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Copies
A digital reproduction of the transcript is available online.
Labor unions -- United States; Personal papers; Business and Industry; Oral histories (Literary genre); Audiocassettes; Interviews; Transcripts; Chief executive officers -- Interviews; Coal mines and mining -- Management; Coal mines and mining -- Pennsylvania; Coal mines and mining -- History; Industrial management; Love, George H. -- Interviews; Pittsburgh Coal Company; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn); National Coal Policy Conference (U.S.); M.A. Hanna Company; Consolidation Coal Company; Chrysler Corporation; Bituminous Coal Operators' Association; National Steel Corporation
- Transcript of Interview (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Ancestors -- The Family Coal Business -- Childhood in Johnstown -- Education, September 19, 1988; 1.
  - Working at Lord and Taylor's -- Harvard Business School -- Lee-Higginson (New York, Chicago, St. Louis) -- Pittsburgh 1926, September 21, 1988; 2.
  - The Coal Industry in the 1920s -- Merger with M.A. Hanna -- Technology in the Coal Industry -- Rockefeller Merger -- Rationalization of the Coal Industry, September 23, 1988; 3.
  - Advantages of Oil and Gas -- Early Experiences in the Coal Business -- George Humphrey -- Creation of Pittsburgh Consolidation Coal -- Pricing Strategies -- Ben Fairless -- R.K. Mellon and the Rolling Rock Club -- The Pittsburgh Renaissance, September 26, 1988; 4.
  - A Horse Named Alfalfa -- John L. Lewis and the Negotiations of 1949-50 -- Directorships of Mellon Bank, GE, and Union Carbide, October 3, 1988; 5.
  - Merger with Pittsburgh Coal (1945) -- Statistics from the 1946 Annual Report -- Public Pricing Policy -- Members of the Consol Board -- Wrestling with Liv Ireland, October 5, 1988; 6.
  - The Fairless Memorial Medal -- The Guffey Act -- Coal Exports in the 1960s and 1970s (the Japanese) -- Mergers with Continental Oil and DuPont -- Management Strategy -- The Chrysler Crisis (1958), October 7, 1988; 7.
  - Building Confidence at Chrysler -- Lynn Townsend -- Management Style, October 12, 1988; 8.
  - Centralized Management (Chrysler, Iacocca, Roger Smith) -- The Turnaround at Chrysler -- The Laurel Valley Golf Club -- Bob Hope and Dolores -- Origins of AEA, October 17, 1988; 9.
  - Seven Keys to Business Leadership -- The Decision-Making Process -- Comments on Today's CEOs -- Mergers and Acquisitions, October 19, 1988; 10.
  - Labor Unions (UMW, USW) -- Techniques of Negotiations -- Serving on a Board of Directors -- Social Responsibilities of Corporations -- Deregulation -- National Industrial Policy -- Eisenhower, October 24, 1988; 11.